So I grew up in Limpopo, on the border of Limpopo
حسنا، لقد نشأت في ليمبوبو، على الحدود بين ليمبوبو
and Mpumalanga, a little town called Motetema.
ومبوالانغا، في مدينة صغيرة تدعى موتيتيما.
Water and electricity supply are as unpredictable
حيث مصادر الماء والكهرباء لا يمكن التنبؤ بها
as the weather, and growing up in these tough situations,
كما هو الحال بالنسبة للطقس، وقد نشأت في في هذه الظروف الصعبة،
at the age of 17, I was relaxing with a couple of friends
وفي سن ال17، كنت مسترخيا مع صديقين
of mine in winter, and we were sunbathing.
لي في الشتاء، في حمام شمس.
The Limpopo sun gets really hot in winter.
تصبح الشمس في ليمبوبو شديدة الحرارة في الشتاء.
So as we were sunbathing, my best friend next to me says,
فبينما كنا نستحم تحت الشمس، كان أعز أصدقائي بجانبي فقال،
"Man, why doesn't somebody invent something that you can
"يا صاح، لم لا يخترع أحدهم شيئا يمكنك
just put on your skin and then you don't have to bathe?"
وضعه على بشرتك بحيث لا تحتاج إلى الاستحمام؟"
And I sat, and I was like, "Man, I would buy that, eh?"
ثم جلست ، فقلت له " كنت لأشتري هذا المنتج لو كان موجودا".
So I went home, and I did a little research,
بعدها عدت إلى المنزل، و قمت ببحث بسيط،
and I found some very shocking statistics.
فوجدت بعض الإحصائيات الصادمة.
Over 2.5 billion people in the world today
ما يفوق 2.5 مليارا من الناس في العالم اليوم
do not have proper access to water and sanitation.
لا يحصلون بشكل لائق على الماء والصرف الصحي.
Four hundred and fifty million of them are in Africa,
450 مليونا منهم من إفريقيا،
and five million of them are in South Africa.
و5 ملايين منهم من جنوب إفريقيا.
Various diseases thrive in this environment,
وتنتشر عدة أمراض في بيئة كهذه
the most drastic of which is called trachoma.
وأخطر هذه الأمراض هي التراخوما.
Trachoma is an infection of the eye due to dirt
التراخوما هي التهاب يصيب العين نتيجة للأوساخ
getting into your eye. Multiple infections of trachoma
التي تدخل للعين. الالتهابات المتكررة للتراخوما
can leave you permanently blind.
قد تجعلك مصابا بالعمى بشكل دائم .
The disease leaves eight million people permanently blind
هذا المرض يصيب 8 ملايين شخص بالعمى الدائم
each and every year. The shocking part about it
كل سنة. الجزء الصادم في هذا الأمر
is that to avoid being infected with trachoma,
هو أنه لتفادي الأصابة بمرض التراخوما
all you have to do is wash your face:
كل ماعليك فعله هو غسل وجهك:
no medicine, no pills, no injections.
لا حاجة لأدوية، ولا حبوب ولا حقن.
So after seeing these shocking statistics, I thought to myself,
إذا بعد رؤية هذه الإحصائيات الصادمة، قلت لنفسي،
"Okay, even if I'm not just doing it for myself
"حسنا، حتى وإن لم أقم بهذا العمل لنفسي
and the fact that I don't want to bathe, I at least need
لأنني لا أريد الاستحمام، على الأقل علي
to do it to try to save the world." (Laughter)
القيام به لأنقذ العالم " (ضحك)
So with my trusty little steed, my Nokia 6234 cell phone --
وبمساعدة صديقي المضمون، هاتفي المحمول نوكيا 6234 --
I didn't have a laptop, I didn't have Internet much,
لم يكن لدي حاسوب محمول، ولم أكن أحصل على الأنترنت كثيرا،
except for the 20-rand-an-hour Internet cafe —
باستثناء تلك التي أحصل عليها ب 20 راوندا للساعة في مقهى الأنترنت --
I did research on Wikipedia, on Google, about lotions,
قمت ببحث في ويكيبيديا وغوغل عن المستحضرات
creams, the compositions, the melting points, the toxicities --
والكريمات والمقادير ونقط الانصهار ودرجة سُمِّية المواد--
I did high school science --
حصلت على شهادة الثانوية في العلوم --
and I wrote down a little formula on a piece of paper,
فدونت صيغة بسيطة على قطعة ورق،
and it looked like the KFC special spice, you know?
كانت تبدو كوصفة كي إف سي الخاصة، تدرون؟
So I was like, okay, so we've got the formula ready.
فقلت حسنا، لدينا الصيغة جاهزة الآن.
Now we need to get this thing into practice.
علينا أن نبدأ الآن في التنفيذ.
Fast forward four years later, after having written
بعد مرور أربع سنوات بسرعة، وبعد كتابة
a 40-page business plan on the cell phone,
خطة عمل من 40 صفحة على الهاتف المحمول،
having written my patent on the cell phone,
بعد كتابة براءة اختراعي على الهاتف المحمول،
I'm the youngest patent-holder in the country,
أنا أصغر حاصل على براءة اختراع في بلادي،
and — ("No more bathing!") —
و-- (" لا استحمام بعد اليوم!")--
I can't say any more than that. (Laughter)
لا يمكنني أن أقول أكثر من هذا. (ضحك)
I had invented DryBath, the world's first
اخترعت "دراي باث" (الاستحمام الجاف) أول مستحضر
bath-substituting lotion.
بديل للاستحمام في العالم.
You literally put it on your skin, and you don't have to bathe.
يمكنك فعليا وضعها على بشرتك، و لن تكون بحاجة للاستحمام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So after having tried to make it work in high school
إذن فبعد محاولة إنجاحه في الثانوية
with the limited resources I had, I went to university,
بمواردي المحدودة، ذهبت إلى الجامعة،
met a few people, got it into practice,
التقيت ببضعة أشخاص، وبدأنا في التنفيذ،
and we have a fully functioning product that's ready
ولدينا منتج جاهز يعمل بشكل كامل
to go to the market. It's actually available on the market.
للإطلاق في السوق. وهو بالفعل متوفر الآن في الأسواق.
So we learned a few lessons in commercializing
تعلمنا بعض الدروس فيما يخص تسويق
and making DryBath available.
"دراي باث" وتوفيره في السوق.
One of the things we learned was that poor communities
أحد الدروس التي تعلمناها هي أن الطبقات الفقيرة
don't buy products in bulk.
لا تشتري المنتوجات بكميات كبيرة.
They buy products on demand. A person in Alex
تشتري المنتوجات عند الحاجة، شخص في آلكس
doesn't buy a box of cigarettes. They buy one cigarette
لا يشتري علبة سجائر، بل يشتري سيجارة واحدة
each day, even though it's more expensive.
كل يوم، حتى وإن كان الثمن أغلى.
So we packaged DryBath in these innovative little sachets.
لذلك قمنا بتعبئة "دراي باث" في هذه الأكياس الصغيرة المبتكرة.
You just snap them in half, and you squeeze it out.
ماعليك سوى أن تمسكها من المنتصف وتضغط عليها ليخرج المنتوج.
And the cool part is, one sachet substitutes one bath
والرائع في الأمر، أن كيسا واحد يمثل بديلا عن استحمام واحد
for five rand.
مقابل 5 راند.
After creating that model, we also learned a lot
وبعد خلق هذا النموذج، تعلمنا كذلك كثيرا
in terms of implementing the product.
عن تنفيذ المنتوج.
We realized that even rich kids from the suburbs
أدركنا أن الأطفال الأغنياء في الضواحي
really want DryBath. (Laughter)
يريدون أيضا "دراي باث".(ضحك)
At least once a week.
على الأقل مرة في الأسبوع.
Anyway, we realized that we could save 80 million liters
على أية حال ، أدركنا أننا استطعنا توفير 80 مليون لتر
of water on average each time they skipped a bath,
من الماء في المتوسط في كل مرة يُتجاوز فيها الاستحمام،
and also we would save two hours a day for kids
وكذلك توفير ساعتين كل يوم من وقت الأطفال
who are in rural areas, two hours more for school,
الذين يعيشون في المناطق القروية، مما يعني ساعتين إضافيتين للمدرسة،
two hours more for homework,
ساعتين إضافيتين للقيام بالواجب المنزلي،
two hours more to just be a kid.
ساعتين إضافيتين ليعيشوا طفولتهم.
After seeing that global impact, we narrowed it down
عندما رأينا هذا التأثير الكبير، اختزلناه
to our key value proposition,
في قيمتنا المقترحة الأساسية،
which was cleanliness and convenience.
والتي كانت تتمحور حول النظافة والراحة.
DryBath is a rich man's convenience
"دراي باث" هو راحة للغني
and a poor man's lifesaver.
ومنقذ حياة للفقير.
Having put the product into practice, we are actually now
بعدما دخل المنتوج حيز التنفيذ دخلنا الآن في الواقع
on the verge of selling the product
مرحلة بيع المنتج
onto a multinational to take it to the retail market,
لشركة عالمية لتطرحه في سوق التقسيط،
and one question I have for the audience today is,
ولدي سؤال أود أن أطرحه على الحضور اليوم،
on the gravel roads of Limpopo,
على الطرق غير الممهدة لليمبوبو،
with an allowance of 50 rand a week,
وبمعاش 50 راوندا في الأسبوع،
I came up with a way for the world not to bathe.
جلبت للعالم طريقة لعدم الاستحمام.
What's stopping you? (Applause)
فما الذي يمنعكم أنتم من جلب أفكار جديدة ؟ (تصفيق)
I'm not done yet. I'm not done yet.
لم أكمل بعد، لم أكمل بعد.
And another key thing that I learned a lot
هناك شيء آخر مهم جدا تعلمته
throughout this whole process,
من خلال كل هذا المسار،
last year Google named me as one of the brightest young minds in the world.
في العام الماضي صنفتني شركة غوغل على أنني أحد ألمع العقول الشابة في العالم.
I'm also currently the best student entrepreneur
أنا أيضا أفضل طالب صاحب مشروع
in the world, the first African to get that accolade,
في العالم، وأول إفريقي يحصل على هذا اللقب،
and one thing that really puzzles me is, I did all of this
لكن هناك أمر واحد يربكني كثيرا، أنني قمت بهذا كله
just because I didn't want to bathe. Thank you.
لأنني كنت لا أريد الاستحمام. شكرا لكم.